Hello! In today's Bug Bounty Report Explained
you will learn how it was possible to exploit
blind SSRF vulnerability in Google Cloud. Blind
SSRFs often have little to no impact but this
time the researcher was able to exploit it
successfully and he got $31,000 for it. Link
to his original blogpost is in the description.
Also, I've recreated the vulnerability and created
hands-on labs. You can try them for free using the
link in the description. You only have to leave
your email. But for now, enjoy the video! Google
cloud monitoring is a service that allows you to
see metrics for your Google Cloud infrastructure.
And Uptime Checks is a functionality that can
send a request to your server to check if it's
okay and potentially notify if your server isdown.
Basic settings allow you to choose the
protocol, hostname and path of your server's
endpoint. So this sounds like a perfect
situation to look for SSRF vulnerability.
And instances that perform those uptime checks
as well work on Google Cloud infrastructure
and as all other virtual machines
they have metadata endpoints on
internal IPs. If we could read a response
from this endpoint using SSRF vulnerability,
we could, for example, steal service account tokens.
So impact of such vulnerability would be critical.
But to protect against SSRFs those endpoints
require a specific header. This can successfully
prevent attacks when the attacker can only
control the URL of the request, but it
won't prevent SSRFs here it's because the uptime
checks feature allows user to set custom headers.
So the researcher tried to request this endpoint
and he saw 200 OK response within 2 milliseconds.
It was a concrete evidence that the server
indeed made the request to the internal IP.
But so far it's only a blind SSRF and
we are not able to show any impact here.
The question is if we can
somehow read the response.
And here, another advanced feature of uptime
checks comes into play - response validation.
You can write a string that you expect to be
present in the response. This could be useful, for
example, in a situation where your server returns
always 200 response code even for 404 responses.
So the easiest way of exfiltrating data
using such functionality looks like this:
we have a part of the response that we know. In
this case, let's assume it's a beginning of JSON
that looks like this. And when you tell the uptime
text feature that you expect this to be present in
your response it's always true because it's always
in the response. But what if we try to search for
such string with "a" as the first letter of the
actual access token? If the uptime check fails
it means that the access token doesn't start
with "a" letter. So then you try with letter "b",
"c", "d" and so on and finally you hit a match,
let's say with letter "e". So now your known part
of the response is one character bigger. So now
you try the same with the access token that starts
with "ea", "eb", "ec" and so on and so forth.
You go over and over again until you exfiltrate
the whole token. That's basically how blind
sql injection is being exploited. This way the
researcher was able to exfiltrate some data but
unfortunately not all of it. Because there was
a small problem - uptime checks are performed
from different instances all over the world.
There were about 54 of them and
each of them has unique access token.
So if your uptime check fails you don't know if
you just tried incorrect character or if you just
hit another instance. In fact, with 54 instances
the chance of hitting another instance is much
much higher than hitting the one you want to hit.
The researcher stopped here, submitted the report
and got the reward of $31.000. The next part of
the video is based on the comment from Google
itself who tried to escalate the issue and created
a proof of concept that was actually able to steal
the access token. One idea is to send 54 requests.
Then, statistically you would hit your instance at
least once. But in practice you wouldn't have the
guarantee and with multiple characters this surely
wouldn't work well. To solve this problem you can
use positive and negative regular expressions.
So in previously mentioned situation you just
sent two filters. Square brackets in regexes
indicate a range of characters. For example, [a-z]
indicates all lowercase letters. A caret means
negative search so [^a-z] matches everything but
a lowercase letter. In this example, we are only
using the "a" character so we don't really need
the square brackets but we will need them in a
second. In such case, when you hit a positive
regex it's awesome you have the next character
of the token. In case you don't have the
positive match but you have the negative
it means that this character is not the next in
the token and you have to try "b", "c" and so on.
If you get neither of those matches you need to
send the same request again, because it means
that you hit the wrong instance. At the beginning
when you only have a few characters of the token
it's possible that tokens from different machines
will have collisions, but we don't care about it,
because we don't target a specific instance but
we want to leak any token.
According to Google,after about 10 characters the token gets unique.
And statistically you would need 54 requests
to hit the correct instance. This means you would
need to send thousands of requests to reveal
the whole token. And those access tokens are
only valid for 60 minutes. So with rate limiting
it's likely that the token would be expired before
you are able to leak it to the end. But we can use
regular expressions to speed-up this process
significantly. First, we can brute force not
only the next character but we can brute force the
whole token using wildcards. The dot stands for
any character in regexes so you can use multiple
dots to brute force all characters in parallel.
This reduces the time of requests significantly.
Another useful trick is using binary search.
We don't need to check each character one by one
like first "a", then "b", then "c" and so on.
Using regexes we can specify ranges of
characters. So we can implement binary search.
First, we can send such request to determine
if the next character is a lowercase letter,
uppercase letter, a digit or any character that
can be inside the token. Let's assume it's a
lowercase letter. The next step is verifying if
the character is within the first or the second
half of the alphabet. Then, you divide that into
further halves until you get to a single letter.
This way you also reduce the number
of requests that you have to send
to determine each character. Of course, the
final exploit must have been really complicated,
because you have to combine all those three
techniques at once. So positive-negative regexes,
binary search and using wildcards to
probe multiple characters at once.
This way the exploit was able to leak the access
token within 15 minutes, including rate limiting.
I recreated the vulnerability in the lab so
you can try your own skills. And you can try
writing your own exploit. You can easily run this
task using docker. To receive the instruction,
you need to leave your email. If you
don't succeed in writing the exploit,
visit my twitter, I will publish my exploit
in a few days. Recreating the vulnerability
in a new application is not an easy task but if
many people will be interested I might do this
more often so let me know in the comments
what do you think about it. And that's it.
I think this way of exfiltrating data will also
allow exploiting other blind vulnerabilities.
Anyway, if you've learned something new today
or you've enjoyed the hands-on labs, leave
a like under this video or maybe even buy me a
coffee. For now, thanks for watching and goodbye!